howdy this is jim rutt and this is the
jim rutt show
[Music]
listeners have asked us to provide
pointers some of the resources we talk
about on the show
we now have links to books and articles
referenced in recent podcasts that are
available on our website
we also offer full transcripts go to
jimrutshow.com
that's jimrutsshow.com
today's guest is hansi frynack coming
back for a
third appearance hanzi was on twice
before when we talked about his two very
interesting books
the listening society and nordic
ideology
we talked mostly about the listening
society in ep 36
and nordic ideology in ep 53
if you want to go deeper on some of the
topics that we talk about today which
will
be broader but not as deep as those
earlier podcasts i recommend that you
take a look at those podcasts and what
we're going to do today
is we're going to explore both
metamodernism and particularly hanzi's
variety which he calls
political metamodernism we're going to
sometimes shorten that to metamodernism
here in our discussion and game b a
perhaps similar but different way of
thinking about the evolution
from where we are to where we're going
for people who want to learn more about
metamodernism
a good place to look is metamoderna.org
in terms of game b there's a very active
game b group on facebook plus 20
satellite groups on specific game b
topics so just search facebook for game
b all one word
and there's also a very comprehensive
wiki at gamebee.wiki
so welcome hanzy good to have you here
again
and the pleasure is on my side it's good
to be back
and you'd be talking to you again jim
yeah we had some wonderful conversations
i look forward to taking it to the next
level
as i was preparing for this podcast i
went through ponzi's books again and
look for quotes that in some sense
overlapped
the political meta-modern perspective
and the game b
perspective and i found i think a good
one from
i believe it's the listening society we
live essentially in a world
our value systems do not correspond to
the society we live in
our ways of seeing sensing feeling
acting
and understanding do not correspond to
the very society that we ourselves
have created this glitch is legal
this is the issue of our age to develop
the political psychology of the world
population
unfortunately stimulating such political
psychological development
is an enormously tricky matter
and that's from hanzi's book and i would
say from the game b
perspective our framing tends to be less
literary and less elegant perhaps
for instance we say that the challenge
is four parts
as humans having gone through our levels
of development
which we'll talk about later we reached
a point where
our power exceeds our wisdom and in
particular there are four challenges
which we can think of as the meta crisis
one is that our agreed weapons and
thirst for power
made us capable of destroying ourself by
force
right we could literally probably don't
kill life on earth probably don't even
kill off humans but we can certainly
knock down advanced civilization and not
only can we do it by intent
our technology has also made us capable
of destroying ourselves by accident
for instance letting loose
nanotechnologies or
engineered viruses that produce some of
the effects that we read in our
dystopian novels
and you know one that's become much more
to the forefront the last
10 years is our pollutants and disregard
for the fragility of nature
made us capable of destroying our
environment which again
could lead to the collapse of advanced
civilization
and the newest one this one is really
disturbing
because as a person who helped invent
the internet some of the communications
platforms and such that exist and not
what we intended i can tell you
but nonetheless i think it's fair to say
our irresponsible use of communications
have made us capable of destroying our
ability to understand and if you think
about the first
three challenges if our modern
communications platforms and the
evolution of them
have made us incapable of sense making
and decision
making so as to address the first three
we're completely
to give a little bit of flavor about
political metamodernism
again get back on hanzi's point of view
it proposes that there's four
dimensions to think about how people
need to change
society needs to change hunting do a
much better job on this than i but he
asked me to do a very brief
introduction and those are hierarchical
complexity which is essentially
how richly does one think and with
what power code which you can think of
as
culture or our social operating system
our state which is what is the typical
state of mind
that our citizens are in are we happy
are we depressed are we agitated
are we in anxiety as our more or less
typical state
and then depth i think this is a really
interesting one we'll talk about its
touch points to game b
in a few minutes which is what is the
range of state that one has had
through one's life so with that i'm
going to turn it back over to hanzi
maybe you can say a little bit more
about political metamodernism
well yes thank you very much so well
starting with the term meta modern
it has to do with well we live in
a late modern society that
is still based around all the key
insights of the enlightenment really
and this includes actually mechanisms
such as
liberal democracy where we cast
votes to substantiate truth claims
really
about the political realities and social
realities
and suggestions that are made really so
we have this inter-subjectivity at the
heart of what we do
which is fundamentally the scientific
method applied to different
fields of life the same goes really for
the capitalist market
where we of course unevenly have the
access to capital to uh to substantiate
which
products should be created on the market
but
nevertheless you have a broad public of
people spending money
and then companies which evolve and
produce the products that
people want or that people verify with
their
with their wallets so to speak and then
of course
this central position of science in
society
and science being a kind of in a way
even a new religion for us
um that we have a sense that there is a
real reality out there an objective
reality
and then this this is modern society and
today we're in a late stage of that
modern society
and the four uh challenges you you
brought up
are are similar to the ones that i like
to bring up i
emphasize the psychological side a bit
more
so saying that well we have um i may
have said this on an earlier episode but
that we have the the sustainability
issue
that modern society is not going to be
sustainable in the long run
and that's visible on so many levels we
live in
all of these spiraling growth mechanisms
and unlimited growth on a limited planet
and
all of these exponential growths of both
output
economic and technological output and
then of course
of the ecological footprint of that and
then
then we have um excessive inequalities
really that
there are inequalities that cannot be
justified
in the world today uh which have to do
with the distribution of resources but
also the distribution of symbolic goods
such as
health happiness and opportunities in
life and so on
and the third one the most subtle one
but perhaps the most pervasive one
is alienation or what mark's called
alienation but
when i use the term i actually have in
mind all of the different
existential issues and
the bewilderment that we feel towards
this late modern life that is coming
apart at the seams that it's
difficult to find meaning and then
john verveiki for instance uh another
i i guess you could say metamodernist
thinker i'm not sure he self describes
as such
um he even terms this a meaning crisis
and some people go ahead and say there
is a meta crisis
of late modernity that all these things
are interconnected
and then people are looking uh for this
golden thread for this pathway away from
this crisis or through this crisis
into a new more stable equilibrium
something you can believe in something
uh that would be utopian or protopian by
today's standards
uh protopian meaning that you actually
can believe in the progress narrative
that you can actually believe
in that hey i can see that this society
is going to get better not that it's
going to grow
and then grow and then the cracks are
going to grow and then
things are going to fall apart at the
seams
so if you ask me what the meta crisis
really really is at the deepest level
and or the most basic level i believe
we have actually a sense-making crisis
i believe that what's broken in the
world
is our shared um
reality checking our shared
um meaning making communication
and verification of claims and realities
so we end up at a terrible distance from
one another
and this is of course visible in
political polarization
it's also uh visible in
post-truth society of all in all its
forms and guises
and also just the fact that we seem to
not be able
to even get down to the basics of what's
real and uh i'll i'd like to
deepen this topic a little bit more but
um
particularly what i see
is that we have collectively started and
i'm not the first to claim this
there were similar terms used by de las
for instance
the the french post-modern theorist
or late post-modern theorist that we're
resembling a schizophrenic collectively
we're starting to resemble a
schizophrenic mind
we're losing grip of reality and we're
really in this
atlas shrugged um position but not
in a heroic way but in a very ah
well in a clearly anti-heroic or
misadventure kind of way so
uh i yeah i think if we're we're looking
for
the deepest solutions we should go back
to
issues of knowledge issues of
reality issues of ontology issues of
communication
issues of philosophy of science issues
of
knowledge processes and knowledge
creation
and claim verification and
somewhere there i see the the most
central issue to be resolved because
if we can't even communicate
about reality we can't even um
if we're at odds about the very basics
of what's real and what the human
condition is and where we're going
then we're highly unlikely to resolve
the profound challenges that we face
yeah i would say that this is where game
b and
political meta-modernism are really on
the same page
the concept of sense making is a core
idea that we both
share in fact one of the game b folks
daniel schmuckenberger
had some incredibly eloquent things to
say about
not only the crisis of sense making but
how we can learn to
to do better with our sense making both
individually and he'll make the point
very importantly collectively
and i point people who want to get most
of daniel's thinking in one reasonably
palatable
piece there's a video on rebel wisdom
called
i think the sense-making crisis with
daniel schmuckenberger number one
there's four of them but the first one
is the one that you really want
to listen to extremely interesting and
as hanzi says if we can't figure out how
to make
sense of our world and have a agreement
at least on the facts
if not on what to do then our chances of
meeting the four challenges
and other challenges are very small
it's interesting he also meant john
vervicky who i would say is at least
game b
adjacent as well as post-modern adjacent
another one of our game b thinkers
jordan hall has
a strong relationship with john verbaki
and they've appeared together on
videos etc and so while personally
those who listen to show know i'm a
little skeptical of
high metaphysics i'm less convinced
there's a big ab meaning
crisis but i am definitely convinced
there's a small
m meaning crisis and that the meanings
that we're making
are not good for either the ongoing
long-term existence of our society or
for our well-being
right you talk about this alienation
and one of the ideas i found very useful
lately has been another one of these
french thinkers
boudryar and his idea of the simulation
and the levels of simulation in which
society has found itself
in and you know one of the things that
afflicts i would argue
many many people in the west in the
united states in particular but also
everywhere you think of the west is that
we are in
many cases living completely away from
actual life the physical realities and
we think that things like
social media is reality or what's on tv
etc we don't know how to change the oil
on our cars anymore we don't have a
garden anymore
in a pinch we wouldn't even know how to
kill a deer and butcher
right and i will raise my hand say i can
do all three of those things god damn it
and people that live deeply in the
simulation
strike me as those who are most likely
to feel alienated and
most likely in a real sense to not feel
that this
strange society we live in is for them
at all
yes so there there is a certain
disconnect
from from reality um in in its
more visceral form and there are many
movements that try to
reintegrate this of course there you
have prepper movements you have
all kinds of new survivalism that shows
up
you have all sorts of workshops where
you dance some prance around and get in
touch with your masculinity
all of which can be good things um so i
i do i do see that
people are responding to these things
however
what i feel is being
missed out on is the
overall big goal
to recreate governance in a way
that communication and truth
verification
and democracy and our institutions of
of uh decision making and legitimization
of those decisions and also
checking with the facts and so on that
they're really breaking down and
of course social media is a very big
part of it and this disconnect from
from everyday reality and here i'd like
to um
actually zoom in on what i meant a
little bit with the schizophrenia part
so uh unfortunately my own family
there has been history of schizophrenia
etc
and i had an old uncle um
a distant uncle when i grew up and he
would write these letters
after he had his schizophrenia had
developed
and these letters would touch on three
topics that would be intermixed or four
topics so
there would all be conspiracy theories
and then in those conspiracy theories
you would find
certain themes that showed up very
strongly
one was pedophilia and conspiracy
theorists with pedophilia and cabals and
stuff like that
another thing was the ufos
and aliens and another thing was magical
thinking
mixed up with astrology and another
thing was a
preoccupation with the nazis in his case
nazis were the bad guys but if you
do take a look at the web today which
is this disconnected simulacra
galore really where people travel
into farther and farther reaches of
combining ideas
and disconnecting really from the lives
that we do live
what do you see well there is the q anon
the a huge conspiracy theory which is
about pedophiles
the new york times on page 17
they publish an article about ufos
as if it's a real thing not on the first
page it's not like they're saying by the
way
we find or actually they are saying on
page 17. by the way ufos are probably
real
and nobody really reacts and
this is growing so the many
scholars that i respect spent years
studying ufology
and they work to make this a more
respectable uh
endeavor which is highly problematic
that we're kind of losing we're not
we're not even
on the same page which kind of reality
we're talking about
and inner and outer reality objective
reality and subjective reality are
getting mixed up here because people
will object you cannot understand my
view of ufos unless you've taken enough
dmt which is also a problematic
statement
but very intelligent very high up
high up in society very powerful folks
are being influenced by these ideas
and taking them seriously together with
that you have all sorts of magical
thinking
they come in many versions they can be
therapy forms
where you change the energies of a
certain kind of
family constellation system or
or healing of different sorts and of
course
healing can sometimes work but for
probably for other reasons then
energy is actually floating around you
have people
intelligent people scholars using
the secret style manifestations
basically that you think about getting
rich and
then you hope that will manifest in your
life
you have increasing prevalence of
astrology
being used therapeutically but also
taking
much much too literally and you have
fascists showing up on different forms
and guises they have showed up in
metamodernist settings
often with explicit sneaky plans to
infiltrate the brand and make it
about some kind of new right
new far right proprietarianism and meta
right and all the rest of it
but basically if you scratch the surface
these are nazis
and they claim to be metamodernists and
you've had a similar problem i know in
the
game b groups and so actually
all of these themes that i recognize
from my childhoods
as schizophrenic uh symptoms
are showing up through the social media
in our own wider community of
progressive thinkers who want to
make a dent in this in this world for
something positive
often intelligent people often sensitive
people often
highly connected highly talented highly
creative people
and well what does this tell us
well we're losing we're losing it
um we're losing grip of reality
collectively
we're fail if we can't even if we can't
sit down and talk about the future of
governance
without having to spend an hour
discussing exo politics
meaning the politics of aliens vis-a-vis
humans
and you have to spend a lot of time uh
or and an effort just to debunk that
stuff
and they will uh always link you to an
infinity of your youtube clips
i mean how on earth are we going to
address climate change or um
the lack of global governance in in a
haywire market society right so
i'd like to like really zoom in on that
topic
and let's try and be creative and find
solutions
for that because i think it's in this
it's in the sociology of knowledge it's
in the processes
of social media but also of governance
and also of communication here
i'd add also and i believe this would be
the game b response to that
is community real community and
you know you didn't even mention the two
most absurd schizophrenic q anon's up
there so let's put q
on in the in the nut bag hall of fame
but we're also seeing a plague of flat
earthers
and anti-vaxxers right another group i
helped found called rally point alpha
which is focused on sense making
you find that on facebook rally point
alpha three words
we don't have too many rules there but
one of them is no anti baxters
right because as you say
they can go on for days pointing you to
all kinds of crazy on the internet
and they'll derail any conversation that
comes anywhere close to public health
with their absurd anti-bacteria stuff
yet the reality is only 100 americans
have died from the side effects of
vaccines since 1950
and god knows how many millions of lives
have been saved so by you know even the
most
cursory examination anti-bacterium is
just plain nuts and yet as you
say
some very intelligent people have
absorbed it
so let's talk about you know in terms of
theory and practice
what is this all about i think actually
your political meta-modern
framework is helpful here we can talk
about hierarchical complexity
which you know kind of shorthand you say
how smart is somebody
and unfortunately our world's gotten too
complicated for the hierarchical
complexity of most people's brains
i mean i see it all the time right you
know the second
is the code social operating system that
we are currently operating
which the game b analysis is has been
hijacked by the short term money on
money
return signal and this is where daniel
schmuckenberger does a great job
he will say that when you're consuming
information
the first question you should ask
yourself is whose economic benefit
was this information created for or in
response to
for instance one of the problems of
science in the sociology of science not
in the engine of science and that's a
distinction i think it's very important
i'm a strong believer that the engine of
science is robust and powerful
but the sociology of science has serious
issues
that need to be addressed is the funding
sources for science which drive
the agenda for science and how careers
are made in science
you know are driven by people who have
vested interests pharmaceutical
companies the defense
complex the intelligence agencies etc so
when you read a paper
uh scientific paper even go read the
acknowledgement section and see who
funded this damn thing
and so our core code our operating
system as we'd say
in game d or our deep code has some deep
flaws in it
that produce strong economic incentives
to skew the information that we're
getting right
and then of course our state one of your
ones in the game b formulation
we point out that learned helplessness
and anxiety about life are
both side products of our current code
right you know united states is worse
than europe in this in the united states
if you're not careful you could actually
end up homeless
right that is not good and so
it seems to me that the attack on this
problem of sense making is unfortunately
you know a pretty hard one there is no
magic silver bullet
daniel schmuckenberger lays out some
things we can do
but it's not easy and i would suggest
that the hierarchical
complexity problem actually speaks to
at least a hint of the direction we can
go which is you know even fairly smart
guys like ourselves
have a hard time keeping up and parsing
what's going on i know i do i don't know
about you
i've done a lot i've read a lot i think
a lot but man
it's really really hard to make sense of
the world by myself
so a game b concept is collective sense
making
is absolutely indispensable and our own
view is it should be bottom up
it should not be top down you should
find other people
who think sort of like we do though with
some variants
and as a group think through the issues
of the day
i'm in a group that meets weekly for
instance to talk about the short term
metacrisis
around the us elections and then
subsequently the
seeming brink of civil war that we're at
these are five
exceedingly interesting smart and varied
people and i think the five of us
together
are making way greater sense of the
world than any of us would make
by ourselves i'm already seeing us all
change our point of views from this
collective
sense making opportunity and i would say
less powerfully but still relatively
powerfully our
online forums dedicated to sense making
like rally point alpha and plenty of
other ones out there
so that's at least a short riff on this
phenomenon that it's
you know fundamentally hard because our
world is more complex than our brains
can be
and that the the code or the deep code
of our social operating system
provides gigantic incentives for bad
faith discourse
not even if it's knowingly bad faith
discourse but it's
all steered by the money on money return
engine
so so there there are a couple of
threads there that are interesting to
pick up
um let's start with the money on money
um well so we do have the open markets
as a way of voting with our money what
makes sense to create
right but as critics of
of capitalism have long uh held and the
post-modernist and post-modern scholars
and french theorists and
among any many others and post-colonial
theorists and
have pointed out is that our
money system is not a very reliable
truth
system because you can always manipulate
what people want
and you can manipulate us through many
many mechanisms that we're not
consciously
aware of so you have all i mean
just what a huge psychological global
experiment it is that we're
funneling this enormous amount of money
into
advertisement and affecting our own
brains
in ways and hijacking our attentions so
that somehow needs to be addressed
on a transnational political level
we want to increase the truth claims
of our emotions that we get we
are equipped all of us with emotional
predictions about what will make us
happy and fulfilled and healthy and so
on
through all of this advertisement that
we're picking up whether or not we do it
consciously
and then we spend our money and efforts
and and
life project and trajectories and goals
according to those assumptions but those
assumptions are often
fairly poor so that's an important part
and that we're we're being fed false
information
a second part that i'd like to a second
thread i'd like to pick up on what you
said is
well let's look at flat earth and let's
look at hierarchical complexity
so flat earth society
is basically a lot of people who have
the intuition that the world is flat
which is the intuitive
belief before people knew that we live
on a globe
sometime in antiquity at least the the
scholars knew by
uh pythagoras time or something
people would assume that the earth was
flat and if you look at it in old
cosmologies viking cosmology
there's a big tree holding it holding up
a disc and so on
and that's kind of the lower complexity
thinking and we all rely
on a sense-making process on a community
bigger than ourselves to create our
reality because it was just up to me
and i was just walking around by myself
in my garden
and had to figure stuff out i wouldn't
get far at all
just like you said so it's not just of
course a group of
of my friends it's the wider community
education
science media and all the rest of it
right
so what used to be in
modernity's earlier phases a fairly
coherent
uh such bond between individual people
and the sense making community
and reality verification mechanism it
has been severed
by the internet because we now can
find these bubbles and then we can
verify claims
and intuitions and conspiracy theories
they pop up with increasing rapidity and
absurdity
uh the same thing with of course flat
earth that people
have this intuition and then they they
can verify
one another and say let's be critical
and they might have difficulties
verifying the stuff
that uh the claims of actual science
and uh actual education within the flat
earth community they will say again
again
please think for yourself and the answer
often is
not to think for yourself the answer is
to have a reliable enough
community to think for you because
hey we won't get very far if we try to
think for ourselves
even on this topic and this actually
collects
it connects beautifully to the issue of
democracy
so political metamodernism is the
opposite pull
of populism so populism is the
lowest common denominator that well in
european countries a lot of people are
irritated by the presence of arabs who
integrate poorly into
their communities and a lot of people
can feel this relatively viscerally in
their
lives and they can see it out on the
street and
well they have events and and uh
and stories about this so this is an
easy topic for populism whereas climate
change
you have to think abstractly you have to
think long term
you're not noticing anything particular
here and now
and you have to trust complicated
predictions which
are admittedly
tentative and you have to
relate that to your own life and to the
politics of your country
and to the market mechanisms and to
technology and the use thereof
so that's a much much more complex issue
and it requires co-development and
requires good
knowledge processes good sense making
processes
and good translation of those sense
making processes
into everyday lives and communities
and that's what we're not very good at
as society today
so political metamodernism will never be
popular it's not going to be like
socialism like a mass
movement and there won't be
meta-modernist
countries or societies which are
nominally meta-modernist
it's rather this funnel towards
higher complexity where we build upon
each other like the scientific community
rather and this goes of course also for
our existential development for our
religious beliefs and so on rather than
falling back
on the lowest common denominators which
our intuitions often lead us towards but
our intuitions fail us
because the world isn't intuitive
humans weren't invented for this kind of
complex world and this complex world
doesn't
just came into being or just happens to
be there and hey
we humans are like heidegger said cast
into it
so the main challenge i think is to
somehow lift
this improvement of the
quality of knowledge making
in to make it into one of the key
political issues of our societies
that governments around the world should
ally and think
okay how can we make our politics much
much more empirical how can we make our
publics our populations
much more critically minded how can we
make
communications how can we arm
or or equip people with
the tools to evaluate truth claims to
evaluate
reference systems out there in the world
i'd like to say more about reference
systems but i'll let you in jim
yeah that was certainly good and
certainly that would be one
path forward and i would say that's a
path that we all need to be working on
and certainly people in the game b space
are working on encouraging these kinds
of things
but you know it's not clear to me that
faced with the fundamental dynamics that
we have that this can be accomplished
top down i mean look at the current
american political mess
we have we have essentially
anti-liberalism of the left and the
right
and then we have an ever-shrinking
number of sensible people in the middle
and you then add to that the current
state of our communications
infrastructure
and we have insanity propagating itself
day by day where
we now have a shooting on the left and a
shooting on the right
and god knows where that will escalate
to so
we're not putting all of our eggs in
that one basket of top down political
change we do think
eventually that has to happen but game b
is more and more
being focused on a day-to-day basis on
localism on building communities
on the ground and on the nets that
can bootstrap and you know and
essentially demonstrate that there's a
better way
i think one of the problems with our
earlier thinking and maybe
the problem with political metamodernism
is that it is more tell than show
and so we believe that we have to put
some effort into showing that
that organizing in certain ways makes
better sense making provides a higher
quality
of life a higher state as you would say
and that at least in a coherent
group we get the effect of hierarchical
complexity even if it isn't in one
person but rather is it a group process
and in fact the four pillars of game b
at least in my version of it
is that it should start from the bottom
and should be self-organizing a skill we
need to get better at
we should use these networks and it's
interesting that while
on one hand social media is destroying
the mass ability to make sense
it's also providing islands of coherence
right the
facebook game b group the facebook rally
point alpha group and
hundreds of others are not the others
where people are using the private
networking capabilities
both those groups by the way have
thousands of members where these tools
can be used constructively
even if the public versions of them are
destructive the third
pillar of game d is decentralized
i think this is perhaps one of the
bigger differences between game b and
political metamodernism is
you know we're pretty strongly believers
in subsidiarity that
problems should be dealt with at the
lowest possible level
that's congruent with their effective
solution and then finally i think we'd
agree on this one
is metastable that society has got to
not exceed its limits and operate in a
way that's
stable for hundreds of years and you say
metastable because no one formulation is
going to be
stable for hundreds of years in the
current world it's going to have to
adapt and fly but be recognizable
itself yeah so uh
there are again several threads i could
pick up let's start
actually with the the top-down bottom-up
thing
i'm not comfortable exactly with being
frame framed as a
top-down proponent rather i think
as i argue in nordic ideology i think
the the solutions are going to be top
down bottom up bottom up top down
meaning that because institutions
have greater explanatory power than
pretty much anything else
in social reality
institutions being habits of many people
which repeat themselves
with regularity so um
[Music]
going to church can be an institution
schools are an institution
forms of governance are institutions and
if you compare
countries which are highly functional
even though they're
not sustainable in the long run and
economies like i don't know south sudan
or something
where there are poor institutions um
the the main difference between the
quality of people's lives
in these destitute places and
uh highly ordered and organized places
like denmark for instance
is that in one place the institutions
are in place and that creates
order and thus freedom that people can
expect what
what happens and they can plan long term
and they can coordinate their actions
across
more space and time including the
actions of their own lives
and thus create better growth
trajectories for themselves and their
families
communities so we are
empowered to create
bottom-up solutions by the social
context we are in
and those social contexts are always
subject to
the economic structures the uh the
sociological
structures and the political structures
of governance within which
we uh we act so
i do believe that political
meta-modernism has to start from the
bottom
in the sense that it has to begin with
people such as ourselves
who are not already enmeshed
in the current system and the many
interests and games that
and and and frameworks and limitations
that are in that
and we can rethink things a little bit
more freely
at a distance nevertheless we then have
to go in
and try to change the institutions and
that's where the
top-down issues come in and those
top-down issues then create
scalable versions of
human growth at a wider level
so what i imagine happening next
in in the world is for
interesting regions they can be
metropolitan regions they can be
geographical regions they can be
uh innovation clusters they can be
communities around the world
they can be web-driven networks
but they need to start to seriously
recreate the life conditions
of everyday life in in
certain key areas maybe a progressive
city like
berlin for instance that what happens if
if berlin gets a progressive game b
oriented
or metamodernism-oriented uh mayor
uh with uh with a wide alliance of the
intelligent people and advisors from
around the world
and then reinvents and deepens
the structures of governance deepens
democracy
deepens how people can participate
in governance um creating
more sovereignty a more sense of
responsibility
more sense of ownership more intelligent
decisions which work with higher
collective intelligence and also gain
higher legitimacy
and at the same time using that higher
democratic legitimacy to improve
the growth processes present in for
instance education
so that kids learn to meditate and
learn to be better perspective takers
um pick up a more systemic view of
reality and society
learn to think more cross-disciplinarily
connect to issues like big history and
and the evolution of of mankind and
technology and
nature itself the the regions that
are first movers in that
in that development in the meta modern
revolution of culture
as it were are going to create more
interesting culture and symbols and
solutions
solutions which manage complexity and
thus can sell well on the market
so they will be competitive on the world
market and will be
able to reinvest a lot of money
into that deeper welfare into that
listening society
and that requires at least some top-down
the top-down
version though is one that reaches
deeper into the grassroots and reaches
deeper into
the human soul and coordinates more
subtle
levels of and subtle layers of what it
means to be a human being so that we are
coordinated
on a deeper emotional level that we have
higher trust for each other for instance
that we
are sexually perhaps more liberated and
expressed
that we are have lesser and fewer
insecurities
that we are better equipped
to communicate around difficult and
complicated and complex topics
so that we can grasp more abstract
goals and organize ourselves around
those more abstract and long-term goals
so i really see it as a both and
i'd like to stop there i still have uh
still have an issue
to bring up on this uh verification
mechanism and and verifying truths back
and forth and so on and how this
tends to break down and i'd like to make
that
a goal of both political metamodernism
and
game b and i do think we should be
looking for
pressure points in the world system
where these things are
actualizable yeah let's get back to that
but let me react a little bit to the
idea of let's say
a meta modern berlin that would be
interesting
if it could actually be pulled off but
unfortunately
you know our modern social operating
systems have a zillion
veto points you know berlin is not
sovereign berlin
lives within one of the german states
brandenburg i believe it is yeah
and brandenburg has its own authority
and then brandenburg lives in a
the german federation lives in the eu
and so the constraints on what the
meta-modern mayor of berlin could
actually do strike me as perhaps
disappointing
our game b approach at this point though
there are certainly people working on
political ideas at a higher level from
fred weinstein's unity 2020 idea of
running an independent candidate for
president of the united states
is at least nominally a game b idea i
think many of us are now focused on a
much smaller
scale to prove the principle which the
label we use for that is
proto-b and literally a proto-b
probably starts out with a cluster of 15
or 20 people
maybe 30 and then aggregates into three
or four such clusters
either on a piece of land or as a series
of co-housing projects
in a city which we call a dunbar which
can actually
operate as a whole game b community with
kb values
decision
in various places using the same social
operating system
and again that's another key point of
our theory is high empiricism
anti-utopianism we don't believe that
you can take
a prescription from a book and say go do
this and build a new world
so not only do we have a proto-b which
replicates via having new dunbars
a little communities of 150 people but
there'll be multiple proto bees with
different constitutions
some of them could be radically
egalitarian i've recently done a fair
amount of research
on kibbutz's in fact we'll have a
scholar on kibbutz's will appear right
before you
on my podcast and kabutz has started out
as radically egalitarian and over time
many though not all of them have evolved
to kind of a mixed
capitalist egalitarian system i expect
proto-b's to do the same
and they may vary with respect to social
class some of them may focus principally
on college educated people
i'm hoping others if i can have my way
one of the early proto-b's will focus
on working-class people and the problems
that they confront in our society
and so again we're really focused on
proving our ideas at a small scale
but with theory that can replicate
gradually and eventually take over
no world in fact i wrote a paper called
a journey to game b
which is on medium and it lays out the
long road to game b which is
more or less as i described could take
100 years 80 years
and of course the other issue is if we
build enough of this
and there's a crisis which we think is
fairly likely there could be a short
road to game b
where let's say there's a couple hundred
thousand game b people out there
and maybe twenty thousand of them
actually living the game b life and
produce
when the crisis comes this might be the
most well-prepared cadre to step forward
to the world and say people look what
we've been doing here's our evidence
it's not just and talk this is
how to organize society and maybe
at that point of crisis there's an
opportunity for a short road to game b
so i think that's kind of the center of
the game b energy at the moment
though because nobody owns game b and it
is radically self-organizing there are
other
tendencies as well but i think that
one's probably the strongest
at the moment and in talking about
institutions
i'm a great believer in institutions
i've designed i believe a better
monetary system for the world you can
find it on youtube dividend money jim
rutt on youtube and you'll have an hour
and a half
talk by me on a better monetary system
and another area that i'm very
interested in is liquid democracy
because that's you point out in your
book hierarchical complexity varies by
person considerably
right and really not much you can do
about it maybe you can raise people's
higher
complexity a bit but not a lot under
liquid democracy the idea is people
proxy their votes
right i had 30 proxies on issues from
education to environment to defense to
health care
i might vote a few of them myself but
there are lots of people who know more
about it than i do
and i would proxy my votes to somebody
who i both had values
alignment with and i perceived to be
more
knowledgeable than i that could include
not-for-profits who specialize in that
for instance i might proxy my
environmental vote to the
sierra club which is a strong
environmental organization here in the
u.s and i might proxy my defense vote to
my retired
air force burn alone and in that way we
can have democracy
and yet not be so constrained by the
strong current limits on hierarchical
complexity
in individual voters so you know with
that i'll turn it back over to you and
maybe we can talk about verification
mechanisms a little bit or you can
respond to
those thoughts yes actually i i do think
for instance liquid democracy can can
have a
role to play in in the larger scheme of
things
i discuss also in nordic ideology i
imagine
that the future
forms of governance that we have will be
uh perpetually
self-improving in terms of institutions
so that i mean a considerable
percentage perhaps even of the gdp
could be invested in improving
governance
itself so that you would have a
democratization
ministerium or or department
and countries learning from each other
and
spreading best practices and there are
many parts of this there is of course
the
uh the digitalization digitization of
democracy and governance and
participation there is participatory
democracy
there is deliberative democracy there
are different forms of direct democracy
including
delegative democracy like like liquid
democracy
there are um many ways in which you can
use
representative democracy there's there
are sortition mechanisms there are
citizen councils and so on and all of
these
i i'm not a strong proponent of any of
particular blueprints so what i imagine
is not
a system that is instituted
and whenever you start talking about
deepening democracy people would
often have a gut reaction say that in
quotation marks wouldn't work and that
system wouldn't work as if they're
speaking about
a particular democratic or a particular
form of governance which is already a
blueprint and already imagined and then
you kind of institute it
that's probably not the the way things
are going to happen
and it would be high too high risk
and too high investment strategy
rather there should be a plethora of
many experiments
powered for instance by game b groups
around the world
which do have uh resources
to experiment with different forms of
governance and self-governance
um and gathering up data really what
works where under which contexts
the same would go for uh commoning and
commons-based solutions in the economy
and to a certain extent i suppose to
cryptocurrencies and alternative
currencies
that we need to on the one hand
have an empirical politics that
it should be the goal of every country
in the world
to stay as close to reality as possible
meaning check the facts check the best
practices
check the best research and all the
different opinions on
it and all the different uh angles and
triangulations thereof
and today we don't have very advanced
processes for that
so empirical politics on one hand
in perpetually increasing our
scientific capability to together grasp
the world and be collectively
intelligent about it
then on the other hand using that
increased empiricism that
self-improving empiricism
viewed as a critical sociological
knowledge process applied
to structures of governance applied to
democracy
to deepening democracy maybe i make this
sound uh much more status than i
intend i don't imagine this is
the this is necessarily top-down
state solution rather i think
we shouldn't ignore the political realm
it has a role to play
but that role is likely to be somewhat
smaller
in fact once once you set up all the
the actual solutions because the private
part the private public partnerships are
there
local communities are engaged civil
society is engaged in many different
ways
the transnational community is engaged
and um looking then at
how do you spread these ideas you
mentioned before well
so berlin is in brandenburg brandenburg
is in germany
germany is in the eu and the eu can
override german laws it's true however
it's also true that one of the most
progressive governments in the world
is actually the european commission
it is considerably more inventive and
progressive
than the governments of the individual
european countries and they're more
experimental
and they examine issues such as
e-democracy
very seriously they also look at things
like alternative currencies
they also look at things like climate
change and they also look at
constructive
solutions for for uh migration and
and resolving uh transnational issues
like that
so what we want is a network or a spider
web
of metamodernly informed or
gay bee type thinkers across the board
who join in an open conspiracy
against the modern world um
that you see the institutions of
modernity
you acknowledge them for their glory and
power
but at the same time you see that the
whole train
is going to go off a cliff and it's
going to be a train wreck
and we have to then try to get off this
trajectory
and towards another one so we want to
empower
networks and individuals across all of
these sectors
and that doesn't have to be antithetical
to
the the game b communities that you uh
that you envision and are already
starting to uh
cultivate rather they should be enmeshed
so i imagine an open conspiracy of
metamodernists or
mighty modernist type people who
are placed across well in the silicon
valley
in in like the heart of tech
in the heart of communication in the
heart of academia
in the un in key ngos
in governance in metropolitan governance
in
local governance in civic projects
around the world on local communities
around the world
but who are aware of each other and
share this meta map
that modernity is awesome
but it's no longer our friend we want to
re-envision modernity hence meta
modernity we want to
see modernity from above and beyond as
it were and redesign it
and not just follow its culture we want
to be creators of its culture
so modern life and modernity and the
enlightenment
taught us to study
nature to reshape nature according to
human human goals
human rationality and so forth but
all of those goals and all that
rationality is still subject to human
culture
which we are not redesigning and
recreating
which creates the a third pillar in my
thinking which is
politics of narrative or politics of
theory or politics of culture
meaning that together we should have
a kind of meta politics a kind of
politics
that envisions which narratives
are defended and
and promulgated out there in the world
and how we make sense of the world
so we should be discussing how we view
reality
we should be creating an open conspiracy
to deepen democracy
and enrich governance and empower
governance around the world
which oftentimes means empowering
bottom-up processes
or most of the time that's what it means
at the same time
doing this with the best possible
empirical processes
and improving upon those empirical
processes themselves seeing that
empiricism is not an either or it's an
impossible destination that we always
have to try to go towards right
that empiricism is the most difficult
thing in the world really
yeah i think we have a lot of agreement
there in particular
in the game b world at least the degree
that i speak for it and i can keep in
mind there are many people that say
different things about game b
that radical empiricism must be the
order of the day
that the nightmares of the 20th century
came from people who had
the answers in a book you know the nazis
and the
marxist leninists and that's not the way
reality works you know one of the things
i've been spending the last 20 years
doing is learning about complexity
science for instance
and the biggest takeaways from
complexity science i describe
as epistemic modesty how little we can
actually predict
what will happen when we make
significant changes to a complex system
like a society
so anyone who thinks they have the
answer whether it's socialism
or propertarianism one thing you can
count on is that they're wrong
rather we can take some principles as
you suggest you know
more democracy and you know preserving
localism and experiment try things and
if they don't work beyond intellectually
honest and say this didn't work let's
try something else you know my writing's
on liquid democracy for instance
i warn every in every essay this is an
interesting idea but it has not been
tried at scale
it may have a huge flaw which i can't
see
so let's try it at the municipal level
first right in a small
city 25 000 people it turns out to be a
show and we can't diagnose a way to
fix the show
let's throw it away and come up with
something else i think that's
tremendously important
as you mentioned these different levels
brings up another bit of language we
we sometimes use in the game b world
which is that these levels of governance
essentially should be fractal that they
should be self-similar that they have
similar values and similar
institutions but they should operate at
all kinds of different scales
you know these same principles can be
applied from a community of 50 people
on up to the global world though of
course with
additions and modifications but we
should we should think about these
things as operating
eventually at all scales so i suppose
the
key question for let's move on to what
do we actually
do right now let's agree we have a
more or less close enough agreement on
the world political meta-modernism
game b don't agree on every detail but
are moving in the same direction
and i'd also call out other folks who
i've run across lately
who i would describe as also on a
similar mission the peer-to-peer folks
michelle bauwens and his people
regenerative ecology
daniel christian wall joe brewer some of
those folks
system changed by doing people a number
of people in california
zebra united architects of the future
a number of these people thinking about
the same kinds of things that you and i
are with a similar heart
and a similar head though with different
emphases and
one of the things that strikes me that
would be useful to do
is to acknowledge that there are
numerous ways to
head towards what comes next and to find
some way for us to more
formally interact with each other and
intercommunicate
and maintain our own points of view but
agree upon what we agree upon
in fact i've labeled this opportunity
the big change coalition
strikes me that that might be a move
that could be
quite powerful that could be done right
now
yes so maybe some kind of world
conference for this
might uh might be a a good step
um where um
people become acquainted uh across these
networks and across
these different ideas and basically
it in
one one of the key tenets of
metamodernism is perspective taking
and the ability to coordinate
many perspectives in a creative manner
not just
critiquing and deconstructing but also
reconstructing
and i think this is a general um
sentiment and impetus that a lot of uh
like-minded people share so what you're
doing with a podcast is important of
course
but we could bring people closer
together i guess
there are already many network meetings
so one of the most important challenges
to those though
are are is this bottleneck challenge
that we
we don't seem to successfully imbue
each other's perspectives because
they're too complex and basically
and each of us is only in the individual
person we have a few
key insights each a smart person
is lucky in their life if they have a
few strokes of genius and a few
theories and perspectives of their own
and we need a lot of those things to be
coordinated so somehow we should get
that
conversation going and not just a
conversation but we should get
constructive projects going around these
things
but to do that i think again
we need to rethink the sense making
process
through which this is organized so just
just bringing all of these smart and
big-hearted people
to the to the same place might actually
not work we
we would then we would first have to
invent
the best possible way of creating
resonance and shared understanding and
shared emergence
and emerge is of course a common thread
a lot of people want to see what emerges
want to kick back and
listen in and stimulate these meetings
and imagine something
fantastic will emerge and it feels like
that it feels like
just around the corner something awesome
is going to emerge
uh something great that will affect and
change the world
i'm a little bit less optimistic i think
we need to be
more creative in terms of how do we
guide this emergence what is the
right process of knowledge sharing
of communication of shared understanding
of decision making
in these varied projects and across them
right
yeah i sense we lack a kind of
a social institutional invention
for gathering all of these diverse
but aligned forces and somehow
coordinating all of these efforts i
would still argue towards
key points in the world pressure points
where
i i imagine something like let's say
that the world right now is having a bit
of a
switching metaphors it's not having
schizophrenia we're having a bit of a
epileptic seizure and the world map is
blinking
with all sorts of dramatic events and
potentials
and we chase after each one of them and
comment upon them and
and try to understand them and then the
next thing happens it's the
covet crisis it's the black lives matter
movement
it's the u.s election all of these
different things right
somehow uh we should be not be
caught up in the epileptic seizure
ourselves we should somehow
see this blinking for what it is
and uh that there are going to be a lot
of dramatic events and there are going
to be a lot of strategic opportunities
for really affecting the trajectory of
the world
and we should be able to coordinate
deeply and strategically around them now
how do we get there
just gathering everyone under the same
roof uh for
uh for shaking hands and uh and giving
half hour presentations would probably
not cut
it we would need some kind of profound
sense making process that is more akin
to the group
of five and the group of 15 that you
were speaking about
interesting i would 100 agree i like the
framing
and in fact you know just sort of
serendipitously
my early thinking about this big change
coalition
has been along those lines interestingly
i've drafted one other person who
resonated with the idea and we're going
to attempt to build a draft core
because one of the ideas i think is very
important is coherent pluralism
the two words are somewhat contradictory
but i think hold them both in your head
simultaneously it's hugely important to
make this work
is that we must be truly honoring the
idea of pluralism
that you know these different points of
view are
perhaps all right or at least are worth
pursuing in their own rights even where
they contradict each other
and that's okay on the other hand for
this thing to be meaningful
there has to be some coherence and one
of the ones
me and this other person just plopped
down and in a couple of emails exchanges
is you know no first degree racists for
instance
right or no nazis if you want to put it
in a more
common terminal we think we'd probably
come up with a couple of dozen
things that are at least candidates for
this potential group to form around
and i think it'd be a great idea to have
a formal sense-making process that
brings
potential candidates to the big change
coalition into a way to interoperate
with each other to discuss what should
be the coherent court
by some consensus process and if
necessary
voting process but consensus would be
better to
you know take some of these candidates
throw them out modify them add some new
ones
and before we have this world conference
unfortunately probably has to be virtual
in the current world
that there is some hands being held
across a group of entities that says yes
this is our coherence
it's relatively small it leaves a lot of
room for
our pluralistic ways of addressing what
we see that needs to be done
but we all at least agree on a small
common core
and so i think that fits in nicely with
the before
part the part that i think needs some
work i think it's very good for you to
point this out is that we also have to
have an after meeting
process to actually turn this into
action how can there be ongoing sense
making
across these groups and horizontal
information
sharing in the game b world we call it x
in a box so
kind of an awkward term but the idea is
if someone finds something that works
they have a duty to document it and
share it horizontally and give it to the
world for other people to use
and if all these different groups that
are on their pluralistic missions though
driven by a coherent core
individually discover things that work
having
a high fidelity communications platform
so that people could look to it to see
what does work
then indeed those x in the boxes could
evolve people take them and modify them
and there's
a liquid democracy 1.0 ah it's been
found to work in a proto-v
in virginia but it had these little
issues right so we're
tweaking it somebody else tries a
variant on it changes a couple things
and said this works better right
and this form of horizontal transmission
of capability could be
really important in kind of the after
meetings
an ongoing kind of mechanism the other
idea which i think
i'm trying to put forth is some of the
glue around this and again it's a little
bit contradictory but that's all right
hold all these in our head is that this
coherence is going to be relatively
small
it has to be to get a large number of
people to buy into it
and so we all have to be willing to have
the cultural meta value of alignment
beyond agreement
meaning that we all acknowledge we're on
the same side even if we fundamentally
disagree
about some tactic or technique that one
of us
takes and that in human history has
shown themselves to be very difficult
the religious wars are quite informative
of that you know
people slaughter each other by the
millions over the most
what seemingly trivial religious issues
so
anyway there's some reaction to your
thought that since making
some process to bring these groups
together it's got to be wrapped in sense
making both before
and after yeah i i think
actually um i i'd like to propose
something a little bit bolder actually
that the coherence should be based
around
goal formulations and
we should have some kind of membership
and constitution
in which the key goals are written down
and then whatever is argued
whatever is proposed to the group as a
project
as a perspective as an alliance
should be coherent with
those goals so
i i would argue that a goal
that is of utmost importance is that
we have to put sense making processes
and higher truthfulness
of the political processes of
communication processes
making society more scientific in a
profound sense but also more
existentially mature
should be our core goals then we can
argue about
what that means in practice
but some kind of directionality some
kind of
transcendent goal is very important
for it not to be discussion club not
only would i
say that the transcendent goal should be
an
inspiring idea on paper to through which
we convene
and then try to materialize different
realities in our
in our meetings and our collisions
we should also ritualize
somehow meaning that there should be
rituals of greeting rituals
of recognition there should be rituals
of conflict resolution
there should be rituals for different
realities being being
different perspectives should somehow be
honored and this is not
super easy but it's at the same time not
inconceivable or not impossible
religions have been
invented in the past for less complex
problems than these but what we're
looking for then
is in a very secular sense now and a
very
abstracted sense a kind of liturgy or
a kind of ritual culture
that can carry all of these complex
diverse minds and experiences
some go deep in the psychedelic
direction some go deep in the
existential spiritual direction some go
deep in the ecological
and animal rights direction some go deep
in the
nitty-gritty of democratic processes
some go deep into
into the intricacies of communication
and uh and startups and entrepreneurship
of different kinds
we need somehow to be able to house
all of these um in one energy container
where people still feel the coherence
where when we feel it
strongly so we feel drawn to it
and this i would like to say also
as a word of warning is what our friends
the fascists are looking for
the the meta right but they imagine this
structure or this transcendence to be
taken
from uh from the traditional religions
or some kind of cathedral building or
some kind of totalitarianism
or some kind of one will that asserts
itself
and some kind of profound unity and
we're not looking for unity we're
looking for as you say
a pluriverse uh a coherent pluriverse
or a complex ontological object is a
term i like it or yeah you said it
better you said
what was the term you used jim coherent
pluralism
coherent pluralism yes so we should
create
as it were a digital temple of coherent
pluralism
uh where these i mean on a very visceral
level
these energies are directed
and i think that is something that we
really need to be doing
now i see all of these geniuses
out there and i see all of these
fantastic ideas on projects
but i see that the coherence is too
small
i also see that a lot of people go crazy
along the way
because because there is no container or
structure which corresponds to
a temple to contain it and what we get
instead then
is that people run off on these on these
fascist experiments because they long so
much for this transcendence
for this oneness and unity ah
yeah very a lot of very good points
there which i'm 100
in agreement with i believe let me first
react to rituals
i think that is really important because
again our world is so
complex relative to our own hierarchical
complexity
that simplification and repetition
actually help us
deal with the complexity of the world
right not having to
figure out de novo how to deal with
every situation
and it reminds me that in the original
game b the 2013
version we actually had a few little
rituals
one was we referred to each other as
peers
you know kind of analogous to the
soviets and their comrades
thing right and we thought that was
really important because we were
anti-hierarchy radically decentralized
we are all peers let's just call
ourselves fears we should go back to
doing that
i don't know why we did the other one
that we had i don't think we ever
actually codified it but i would call it
explicit and excessive politeness right
we never ever until they started to fail
then the group fell apart
were we anything other than with very
polite with each other
right and excessively so almost like a
frenchman in court
in louis the 14th day or something right
we would very much defer to the other
person
we would apologize very easily and
quickly
should we give offense etc kind of a
stylized explicit politics
might be an interesting ritual as an
example
that could help push away the known
problems
of dealing with people particularly in a
non-face-to-face
fashion but anyways certainly it's worth
some serious
thoughts and what those rituals would be
right that could be a process to think
about
propose and either adopt by consensus or
reject or modify possible rituals as
part of this formation process
i like it i think it's neat but then the
other one which is something
close as a goal formation at least as an
intermediate
goal sense-making and truthfulness i
think is
really good in fact the two bases
of game b which came from a conversation
jordan hall and i had
at the santa fe institute in 2008 it
were honesty and good
faith and we've always said that game b
has to be a world in which honesty and
good faith is a winning strategy
but not the sucker strategy that it is
in late modernity
and not far from sense-making and
truthfulness
and i think somewhere in that space we
can find a goal formulation
that a fair number of people would agree
to so i think that's good
and of course people are going to have
different ideas about what
truthfulness means but as you said with
the politeness
part that if if we can show it don't
tell it
if we can create a culture around it
then perhaps we can contain more of this
energy
um and i mean the energy is tremendous
really and and it's part of why the
world is flipping out so much
people are having all of these profound
spiritual experiences people are having
all of these intellectual awakenings
people are waking up to
systems perspectives cross-disciplinary
perspectives pop people are trashing
their old
world views they're getting into
entirely new networks of people
um and at the same time
you see a lot of these people not
knowing what to do with
with all of these things that they
access often through through the web
and being unable to to
create something in their own lives
around it and to be able to create
something in our own life
uh we often need companionship then
so if we can increase uh
the amount of friendship between
what i would loosely term all the
meta-modernists out in the world
the key the key element would be a kind
of
camaraderie or friendship and the
alliance would be against the modern
world but not
now with a very strong caveat
not the integral traditionalists or the
transcendental fascists who
who want to build cathedrals rather than
skyscrapers again
and dismantle democracy and stuff like
that
but rather a conspiracy against the
modern world but a call not from the
past not a blast from the past but a
blast from the future
and uh somehow placing ourselves in a
future protopian vision uh
being in that transcendental space being
in we are inventors of the world we are
inventors of culture
we are going to invent rituals with
which we can
with which we can convene as not just
intellects not just dry intellects but
as whole human beings
and there are there are four different
parts of this
uh um creative class which i feel is the
is a very instrumental to the
metamodernist movement and
this class has yet to wake up to its own
uh to its own coherence because it's so
diverse but there are
deep uh there are deep structural issues
which
connect its members and i've said this
before it's a triple h population it's
the
hippies people who are good at inner
development spirituality shamanism
and all the rest of it and maybe taking
indigenous perspectives
there are the hackers who the silicon
valley types who can
understand and reinvent information and
its flows
there are the hipsters more my own type
who are good at understanding culture
and
philosophy and seeing how
how new symbols and new meanings can be
can be created in the world and new code
can be created to to run
our culture and then there are there's
the fourth
age which wasn't in the listening
society it has been
added later the hermetics the people who
are more
towards the occult side arguably perhaps
the most dangerous group
because they love all of these symbols
and they love all
of these rituals so much and they look
so so deeply for the meaning in these
that they can sometimes fall into
traps of uh well unhealthy occultism or
even
even far-right stuff but the
hermetics are the experts on creating
these
new games on these new rituals so we
somehow need to
draw on all of these four competencies
uh
which really they can't be situated
within one person because each of them
takes so much
talent and so much personality and so
much of your
uh core being to develop that people
have these different specialties and yet
together they are all part of
well not they don't fit in in modern
society
they have a specific class interest
which is transnational and it doesn't
like the top-down
governance structures they don't fit in
the labor markets they all
often fall down and precarious positions
uh flip out for reasons
that have they they often have adhd and
add
sometimes uh high functioning autism
so somehow uh the temple i
imagine uh for for game b
uh the virtual temple which has this
transcendent goal
has to draw all of these four groups
and let these energies intermingle and
then i think
actually the solutions are likely to
come because all of these people are
talented
and inventive and already connected
and with more proper support
they're likely to be more successful in
society at large
meaning well they can get into uh
politics if that that's what they want
with the support of their
like-minded people and a very very
important part of this
is to set up a really
robust structure to protect the mental
health
of these groups because what we're
seeing also
is that they keep flipping out
and and here we are we're trying to save
the world
we're chasing each other on the web
trying to communicate trying to
understand
each other and climate change is ongoing
political decay is ongoing democracy is
on demise
chinese autocracy is on the rise
digital autocracy is on the rise um
troll factories are controlling the the
public discourse the media
has a really hard time making sense of
all of this using all the old
uh uh paradigms to to interpret it
so i think just the fact if we could do
one thing if we could
get a group of 10 000 of the four
quadruple age population from around the
world to
really know each other in in groups of
we would have a lot of the situated
projects that
i imagine either way right
yeah i love it you know there's a lot to
it as you were saying that
you have the hermetics i thought that
was very interesting because one of the
groups that we're
now catalyzing in game b we call them
the
archetype narrative people yeah yeah
that works to
too i like ages right so so it's going
to be quadruple age right
yeah yeah and i said yeah we certainly
got hippies really got hackers we surely
have hipsters
and we're adding in the hermetics that's
kind of an interesting maybe overloaded
term but for it makes another
nice h why not right and again i think
this is one of the reasons there's this
libido within game b
right now to actually produce groups on
the ground
is the concern you put in about mental
health
right that people are just finding it
stressful as
to have these insights about the world
how deeply screwed we are
and yet there is a way forward and yet
we're not taking it and to do this
as one person living in your mother's
basement
in bavaria as one particular person i
know
is is very bad for their mental health
right
and if they were to live in a community
of somewhere between 30 and 150 people
that's well populated with the 4hs plus
some other skill sets
and they have meals together in common
and they have conviviality
parties on a regular basis they sing and
dance together
you know this could by itself
fundamentally
upregulate people's mental health we're
not designed to be alone
you know we are acculturated creatures
and those few of us who started to break
free of
the culture that were embedded in you
know experience a fair amount of stress
from that and some people can handle it
and some people
can't and so building communities on the
ground
in which people are embedded in a
like-minded proto culture
strikes me as i can see why there's such
demand for that right now
so i really like what you said before
about uh politeness
and i i think you know on on the
modernist
forum we only really have two rules and
it's
um kindness and respect and don't spam
and that's it but then later on
i've added inofficial ones and it's no
ufos
no uh magic and no nazis
those are kind of an immune system um
because
hey openness uh has a cost
and there is you kind of have to pay
a certain a certain cost to to imbue new
information to respond and so on
and we have to put some limits on it so
to make this filter on open one but an
effective one
so that perspectives are drawn in widely
and
but still still don't devolve
right so these are these are perhaps
necessary
at this point other than that there are
certain norms
that i think should be very important
for instance
um there are rituals for many things in
our societies but there's not a real
ritual for
honoring when somebody changes their
mind
rather we tend to lose prestige when we
do
so somehow this this needs to be turned
on its head
should be an honorable thing to do to
listen in
take up somebody else's perspective and
argument and change one's position
doesn't mean uh it doesn't mean being a
pushover or anything like that
it just means that we get stuck
in all of these discussions which are
not
necessarily conducive to creative
solutions or to mental health for that
matter or to good relationships and
friendships
but if we had a norm
a strong norm which says it's okay to
change your opinion and you're expected
to do so
fairly often then we could
evolve together more quickly really
and and coordinate on a deeper level
yeah we're explorers right and explorers
expect to learn new things right
i absolutely agree that's an excellent
and of course this
kind of weirdo thing called cancel
culture is
exactly an opposite of that right so
they hang somebody from the lamp post
because it's something i said in 1985
right that's ridiculous people aren't
who they were in 1985
you know the world has changed a lot and
so honoring the fact that we can
can and do and should change over time i
like that a lot as
kind of a meta ritual for this what
comes
next movement well i think we're getting
kind of long here on time as we always
do
but we always have such good
conversations it's hard to keep them
within the bounds of an hour and a half
podcast but i think this has been an
exceptionally rich and
fruitful discussion i hope that we can
continue to
maybe take some active steps to bring
these things into being afterwards
yeah i think we have a good plan to take
over the world so uh we should
definitely i mean let's see what what
people how people respond to it
and see if this uh our formulations here
speak to people
and um maybe if we have a critical mass
of people who would like to get
something like this
afloat uh a very intentional
community of truth-seeking which is an
open conspiracy against the modern world
which tries to bring us to a new
equilibrium of
a more sustainable development and more
inner development
and relational development than
hay hey i think we can go get buried
with satisfaction right because then we
would have taken
a good meta step towards this new world
we want to see
production services and audio editing by
jared james consulting
music by tom muller at
modernspacemusic.com